# 哈喽 大家好
Hello, everyone.
# 我是王刚
I'm Wang Gang
# 本期视频我给大家分享一道拿手菜
In this video I want to share with you my specialty -
# 珊瑚鱼
"Coral Fish"
# 首先我们准备一条三斤左右的草鱼
First we get a ~3 Jin (1.5kg) grass carp
# 用刀拍晕鱼头之后
After hitting on its head and putting it into coma,
# 在颈部切上一刀
cut into its neck.
# 这一步的目的是切断草鱼的神经防止跳动
This step is to cut the nerves so that it doesn't flop
# 然后用小刀将鱼鳞刮干净
Then use a utility knife to scale the fish
# 鱼鳞刮干净之后剖开鱼肚
Cut open its belly
# 然后去除各种内脏和鱼鳃清洗干净备用
Then gut and gill the fish, and clean it up
# 下一步开始准备分解
Next we prepare to dissect the fish
# 将鱼从中间片开之后再按照步骤取下鱼肉
Slice the meat from the middle following these steps
# 同学们取鱼排的时候必须贴着肉往下滑
You must touch the bones and cut downwards
# 否则鱼肉不规则也无法切成
Otherwise the final fillet won't be regularly shaped,
# 长条完整的珊瑚
and unsuitable for the next step.
# 由于此菜不需要用到鱼头和鱼骨
Since we don't need the bones and head,
# 分解下来的鱼骨和鱼头可以安排煮汤
they can be used for later making soup.
# 下一步我们开始切珊瑚
Next we start cutting out the coral shape
# 首先我们斜刀切下第一片鱼肉不用
First we slant-cut the first piece and desert it
# 然后继续斜刀将鱼片间隔一厘米左右
Then continue slant-cutting at 1cm spaces,
# 切至鱼皮不断
and keep the fish skin intact.
# 鱼皮的厚度大约保持在三毫米左右
Fish skin is about 3mm thick
# 同学们切记不能片得低于三毫米
So be careful not to cut too much into that 3mm,
# 否则鱼片切丝或者上粉的时候容易抖断
or the whole slice can break in later steps.
# 然后我们看一下切好的成品
Let's take a look at the final shape
# 下一步开始切丝
Next we cut them into strips
# 这一步我们将鱼肉朝上放到菜板上面
We want to put the fish vertically on the chopping board in this step
# 然后一片一片翻过来用刀根部往外推切成细丝
Then flip each piece over and use the end of the cleaver to cut each piece into strips
# 同学们切记这一步至关重要
You must remember this step is crucial
# 必须是菜刀根部先着地往前滑
You must make the end of the cleaver touch the board first and then slide forward
# 刀角切下的位置必须顶着鱼皮
The rear side of the cleaver must touch the fish skin
# 这样切出来的珊瑚才够直观好看
This ensures the final "coral" looks real and appealing
# 还有一种方法是将鱼肉冰冻之后再用剪刀裁剪
Another method is to freeze the meat and cut with a pair of scissors
# 鱼肉冰冻后再裁剪到出成品
The whole freeze-and-cut process
# 大约需要四小时
can take about 4 hours.
# 由于时间比较慢
Considering the long hours spent,
# 所以已经淘汰
we've abandoned that method.
# 专业厨师按照此法改刀出品
Professional chefs now use this type of cutting
# 只需要15分钟即可上菜
It reduces the whole cooking and serving process to 15 minutes
# 下一步开始初加工
Next we pre-process the fish
# 首先我们将鱼肉放入清水中清洗干净
First we clean the meat with fresh water
# 这一步可以去除鱼肉之间残存的血水和细小的肉粒
This step is to remove blood in veins and wash away detached meat dices
# 清洗干净之后将鱼肉捞出
Then take it out
# 鱼肉捞出之后准备一张干净的毛巾
Get a clean towel
# 将鱼肉放到毛巾中折叠起来
Then wrap the meat inside
# 轻轻的挤压几下吸干多余的水分
and lightly squeeze out the water.
# 这一步的目的是方便下一步腌制吸收调料的味道
This step is to make it easy to later absorb the seasoning
# 下一步我们开始准备腌制
Next we start marinating
# 碗中加入食用盐一小勺
Add one small spoon of salt into a bowl
# 加入适量的黄酒搅拌均匀备用
and some huangjiu rice wine, and mix well.
# 没有黄酒的同学也可以用料酒代替
You can use Chinese cooking wine if you don't have huangjiu rice wine
# 然后将吸干水分的鱼肉腌制两分钟
Then marinate the meat for two minutes
# 同学们切记不能加胡椒粉
You must not add black pepper powder
# 否则成菜会有糊辣味
Otherwise the final dish will be hot and spicy
# 两分钟之后加入玉米淀粉一大碗拌匀
Two minutes later add a large bowl of corn starch and mix well
# 玉米淀粉可以控制鱼肉松软的口感
Corn starch can stiffen the soft fish meat
# 喜欢外酥内软的同学可以全程加玉米淀粉
If you like the "crispy outside tender inside" style, you can keep using corn starch for later steps
# 然后加入土豆淀粉一大碗均匀的拍上
Then add a large bowl of potato starch and cover the fish
# 这个过程必须拍到位不能放过每一个细节
You must not miss any corners
# 加土豆淀粉可以让鱼肉长时间的保持脆爽
Potato starch can keep the meat crisp and juicy
# 玉米和土豆淀粉的比例大概为3:7
The corn starch to potato starch ratio is about 3:7
# 下一步开始调碗汁
Next we prepare the sauce
# 碗中加入番茄酱300克
Add 300g tomato sauce to a bowl
# 加入白醋40克
Add 40g white vinegar
# 加入白糖120克
Add 120g white sugar
# 搅拌的中途再加入少许的食用盐
Add a little bit of salt while mixing
# 下一步开始制作
Next we start cooking
# 首先我们把锅烧热
First heat up the wok
# 锅烧热之后加入宽油（植物混合油）
Then add Kuan You (literally "broad oil")
# 油量大约为五公斤
About 5kg
# 然后将油温烧至六成热
Then wait till oil temperature is about 180°C
# 油温六成热之后将鱼肉的淀粉稍微抖一下
When oil temperature is about 180°C, shake off excessive starch on the meat
# 双手拉着两边下锅炸
Hold both sides and fry
# 略微定型之后再放手将鱼肉下锅中小火炸三分钟
When the fish stiffen, put it in and fry 3 minutes
# 同学们火候的变化分两个阶段
There are two temperatures that we need to pay attention to:
# 下锅前两分钟小火略高（5成油温）
Two minutes before putting the fish in, we are at low heat.
# 油温大约150度
The oil temperature is about 150°C.
# 第二阶段在两分钟之后开一次中火将油温提升15度
The second temperature measure is at two minutes later. Now we raise the temperature by 15°C on middle heat.
# 三分钟之后将鱼肉捞出
Three minutes later, take out the fish
# 鱼肉炸好之后捞出将其堆叠摆盘即可
Arrange in a plate
# 刚捞出来的鱼肉非常的烫手
The meat is very hot
# 建议不抗烫的同学带防烫手套
You may want to wear some heat-insulating gloves
# 或者待其稍微冷却之后再操作
Or wait till it cools
# 宽油倒出之后再加入少许的底油开始烧汁
Empty the wok and add some base oil to make the sauce
# 然后直接将调好的番茄汁下锅
Then pour straight in the tomato-based sauce just made
# 中火烧滚之后再加入适量的清水稀释一下
Use middle heat and dilute it with some water when the sauce comes to a boil
# 再次烧开之后将锅离火
When the sauce boils again, remove from heat and
# 然后少量多次的加入水淀粉拌匀
add slurry little by little with mixing.
# 淀粉拌匀之后将其烧开
Then boil again
# 最后再加入少许的明油分两次加入
Finally add some Ming You (literally "oil for a shiny presence") twice
# 第一次加入的明油将其拌匀
Mix the first half well with the sauce
# 第二次加的明油不动
Leave the second half unstirred
# 料汁烧好之后直接出锅淋在炸好的鱼上面即可
Spread the sauce over the fish
# 最后可以撒上自己喜欢的点缀即可上菜
Finally add some herbs in complement and serve
# 一道口感酥脆味道酸甜的珊瑚鱼就制作完成
A crispy-tasting and sweet & sour "Coral Fish" is finished
# 下面开始技术总结
Now for the technical tips:
# 第一工具的选择
First, choice of knives
# 首先我们会用到三把刀
We need three knives:
# 分别是砍刀 小尖刀和片刀
they are cleaver, utility knife and slicing knife.
# 第一次使用的是砍刀
We used cleaver, at the start,
# 用于拍晕草鱼和开边剁骨
to hit grass carp and cut bones.
# 第二把是小尖刀用于刮鱼鳞和开膛破肚
Then we used utility knife to scale and gut the fish
# 第三把是片刀
The third knife we used was a slicing knife
# 此刀刀身宽薄长
It has long and narrow blade
# 用于片鱼和切丝
Suitable for slicing fish and cutting strips
# 第二
Second,
# 用砍刀横切整个鱼的时候
when separating the meat from the bone,
# 刀锋略朝下贴着鱼肉滑过
we need to point the knife blade slightly downward and slide across the bone.
# 这样可以留下绝大部分的鱼肉
This is to cleanly separate the meat from the bone
# 同时新手操作的时候
It may be easier for novices to
# 左手可以用毛巾垫着抓鱼
use a towel when holding the fish.
# 这样可以防止粘液滑手撞刀
To prevent slipping and accidentally cutting yourselves
# 此段演示错误的操作
This is an incorrect demonstration
# 由于刀锋朝下
The blade points downward,
# 且没有贴着鱼的脊骨取肉
but it doesn't touch the bone.
# 所以取下的鱼肉呈现不规则也不美观
So the final piece is not regular and not appealing
# 第三取鱼排的时候同样需要
Third, when making fish fillets out of a whole fish,
# 贴着排骨往下切
it's the same technique of pointing downward and cutting along the spine.
# 这样除了美观之外也能提升草鱼的出肉率
This makes the fillet looks nice and reduces waste
# 同时酸菜鱼水煮鱼也是以此类方法取肉
This technique can also be applied when making "Suan Cai Yu: (literally "Sour Vegetable Fish") and "Shui Zhu Yu" (literally "Water Boiled Fish")
# 第四片鱼的时候取掉第一片鱼肉不要
Forth, the first slant-cut piece of meat is deserted
# 然后以20至25度斜刀切至鱼皮处
Then slant-cut at an angle of 20 to 25 degrees until touching the skin
# 右手拿刀切的时候用力必须均匀
Keep a constant force on your right hand
# 这样鱼片才能够一致
so that the pieces are uniform.
# 同学们切记不能将鱼皮切断
You must not cut break the skin
# 否则断一刀就能废掉一整个菜
One wrong cut and the whole dish is wasted
# 第五
Fifth,
# 我们再来复习切丝的技巧
let's review some julienning techniques.
# 切丝的时候尽量把每一片鱼肉实打实的贴在菜板上面
Make sure each piece is indeed laid attached to the board
# 切完一片再拿另外一片下来切
Finish one piece and then continue to flip over the next one
# 偶尔断一两根属于正常现象
Breaking one or two strips during this process is normal
# 第六
Sixth,
# 抖粉之前必须将鱼肉清洗
Wash the meat thoroughly before covering with starch
# 且用毛巾将水分粘干
Use a towel to dry completely
# 抖干淀粉的时候必须每一处都很均匀
Starch must cover every part of the meat
# 鱼肉下锅炸之前不能有湿润的地方
There has to be no wet places
# 否则下锅容易粘成一团
Otherwise meat may become attached in a jumble
# 最后在淋汁的时候如果不赶时间的话
If there is no time constraints at the final step,
# 可以用小汤匙少量多次的淋在鱼上面
you can use a small spoon to fully spread the sauce.
# 珊瑚鱼的技术总结完毕
That's all for the technical tips